<resources>
    <string name="app_name">ChemEasy</string>
    <string name="button">Button</string>
    <string name="title_activity_quizzes_menu">QuizzesMenu</string>
    <string name="title_activity_theromdynamics">theromdynamics</string>
    <string name = "intro_to_history_of_the_atom_content">One of the greatest challenges in the 19th century
was how to construct a working model of an atom. The
idea of an was first proposed in ancient Greece, but
only about 2000 years later did this concept regain
momentum. Many scientists proposed different atomic
models, with each one evolving from the previous model.</string>
    <string name="dalton_content">"John Dalton became the first major scientist to put forth an atomic model.
He proposed that atoms were similar to hard balls, giving his model the name The Billiard Ball Model.
With this model, Dalton hypothesized:
    1) Atoms were fundamental entities that could not be split
    2) An element consisted of only one type of atom
    3) During reactions, atoms rearrange to form new compounds"</string>
    <string name="thomson_content">In 1897, J.J Thomson discovered the electron, a negatively charged particle smaller than an atom. Thomson proposed that an atom consists of a positiviely charged cloud with negatively charged electrons scattered throughout.</string>
    <string name="rutherford_content">In 1911, Rutherford conducted a gold foil experiment,where he saw that very few alpha particles were scattered after striking gold foil. This disproved Thomson\'s notion that the mass in an atom is distributed evenly, and that almost all of the mass was concentrated towards a small area the center, called the nucleus. The nucleus is positively charged and has electrons surrounding it.</string>
    <string name="bohr_content">In 1913, Niels Bohr had a revolutionary proposal for atomic models. Bohr agreed that an atom had a positively charged nucleus on the inside with negatively charged electrons surrounding the nucleus. However, he was the first to believe that electrons moved around atoms in orbits. Each orbit corresponded to a specific energy level.</string>
    <string name="schrodinger_content">It is accepted that the most accurate model is Schrodinger\'s model. Schrodinger proposed that electrons move in waves and not clear paths. Therefore, it is impossible to determine the exact location of an electron; there are only clouds of probability of where an electron might be.</string>
    <string name="parts_of_an_atom_content">The experiments outlined previously show that an atom is composed of three main subatomic particles: protons, neutrons, and electrons. The characteristics of each of these particles is outlined in the table below.</string>
    <string name="em_spectrum_content">The electromagnetic spectrum is the range of all wavelengths and frequencies of electromagnetic radiation. Electromagnetic radiation itself consists of basic units called photons. The electromagentic spectrum, while vast, is mostly invisible. The electromagnetic spectrum consists of the following major areas.  \n- Radio waves  \n- Microwaves  \n- Infrared Light  \n- Visible Light  \n- Ultraviolet Light  \n- X-rays  \n- Gamma rays</string>
    <string name="zeroth_order_content">In a zeroth order reaction, the reaction rate is independent of reactant concentrations. When graphed over time, the graph of the concetration of the reactant would have a slope of -k, while the concentration of the product would have a slope of k.</string>
    <string name="zeroth_law_content">The zeroth law of thermodynamics that if two thermodynamic systems are each in thermal equilibrium with a third one, then they are in thermal equilibrium with each other. Basically, if system A is in thermal equilibrium with system B and system B is also in thermal equilibrium with system C, system A and system C are in thermal equilibrium with each other.</string>
    <string name="weak_acid_strong_base_titration">When a weak acid is titrated with a strong base, the graph will start out with a pH of between 4-6, have an equivalence point above 7 pH, and end with a high pH. Since the strong base dominates, the solution at the equivalence point will be basic.</string>
    <string name="vsepr_theory_content">The VSEPR (Valence Shell Electron Pair Repulsion) Theory allows us to predict what shape a molecule will take. We can use the number of atoms and the number of lone electron pairs on the central atom to determine the resulting shape. Each shape has its own bond angles and hybridization. It is notable that certain shapes have a certain formula associated with them.</string>
    <string name="transition_metals_content">"Transition Metals are found in the middle of the periodic table, in groups 3 - 12. Transition metal ions have varying charges.

Some characteristics of transition metals include:
  - form colored compounds
  - less reactive than alkali and alkali earth metals
  - high melting points (with the exception of mercury(Hg))
  - ductile and malleable"</string>
    <string name="titration_curves_content">We can model titrations using titration curves, which are graphs that map the pH of a solution depending on the titrant added. A significant part of a titration curve is the equivalence point. The equivalence point is the point at which the moles of titrant (standard solution) equal the moles of the solution with unknown concentration. One will know they have reached the equivalence point when the solution begins to change color towards the indicator. The endpoint refers to when the solution is the same as the color of the indicator.</string>
    <string name="third_law_content">The third law of thermodynamics states that the entropy of a system approaches a constant value as its temperature approaches absolute zero. Also, the entropy of a pure, perfect crystalline substance at 0 K is zero. In the image above, the left image shows a substance at absolute zero, with no entropy, since all particles are stationary. In the right image, as temperature increases, the number of particle arrangements also increase, thus increasing entropy.</string>
    <string name="temperature_solubility_content">Temperature effects solubility of solids, liquids, and gasses differently.   Solids: In an endothermic reaction, the system shifts to the right(products). This causes more of the solid to disassociate, which increases solubility. Meanwhile, in an exothermic reaction, the system shifts to the left(reactants), so less of the solid is dissolved when the equilibrium is re-established. This decreases the solubility   Liquids: There appears to be no correlation in regards to temperature affecting solubility in liquids.   Gasses: In general, increased temperatures mean lesser solubility and decreased temperatures mean higher solubility. This is because the process of dissolving gas in liquid is usually exothermic. Then, increasing temperature shifts the reaction towards the reactants which decreases solubility, while decreasing pressures shifts the reaction towards products, increasing solubility.</string>
    <string name="system_and_surroundings_content">To understand energy, we must first understand what a system is, and how it is different from surroundings. A system is essentially the reaction being studied, while the surroundings is the rest of the universe. In the picture above, the water and ice in the beaker is the system, while the surroundings includes the beaker, air, and everything else in the universe.</string>
    <string name="strong_and_weak_bases_content">Strong bases completely disassociate in water, leaving behind hydroxide and a cation. They typically have a pH from 12 - 14. Some examples of strong bases include hydroxides of alkali metals and alkaline earth metals like sodium hydroxide (NaOH) and calcium hydroxide(Ca(OH₂)).    Weak bases disassociate partly in the water. In solution, the result is a an equilibrium of the base itself, and the products of disassociation. An example of a weak base is NH₃. Weak bases typically have a pH between 7 and 10.</string>
    <string name="strong_and_weak_acids_content">Strong acids completely disassociate in water, leaving behind a proton and an anion. Strong acids typically have a pH between 0 to 3. Some examples of strong acids include hydrochloric acid (HCl), hydrobromic acid (HBr), hydroiodic acid (HI), nitric acid (HNO₃), and sulfuric acid (H₂SO₄)   Weak acids disassociate partly in the water. In solution, the result is a an equilibrium of the acid itself, and the products of disassociation. Weak acids typically have a pH between 5 and 7</string>
    <string name="strong_acid_weak_base_titration_content">When a weak base is titrated with a strong acid, its equivalence point will be at a pH of less than 7. Since the strong acid dominates, the solution will be acidic at the equivalence point.</string>
    <string name="strong_acid_strong_base_titration_content">When a strong acid is titrated with a strong base, the graph will start out with a very low pH, have an equivalence point at 7 pH, and end with a high pH.</string>
    <string name="spontaneous_processes_content">A spontaneous process is a process or reaction that occurs without an external input of energy. An example, shown in the picture above, is the rusting of iron.</string>
    <string name="specific_heat_content">Specific heat refers to the heat required per unit mass to raise the temperature (typically in Celsius) of a substance by a given amount (usually one degree). The table above shows some specific heat values for common materials. Notice that metals tend to have lower specific heat as they are conductors of heat, and thus, do not require as much energy for a temperature change. Specific heat is will be important in finding the ammount of energy needed to cause a phase or temperature change.</string>
    <string name="solute_solvent_interactions">As a general rule of thumb, like dissolves like. That is, a polar solvent will be able to dissolve a polar solute, while a nonpolar solvent will dissolve a nonpolar solute. If a polar solvent and nonpolar solute are combined (or the other way around), there will be little, if any, solubility.</string>
    <string name="solids_content">Solids are formed by tightly packed atoms held together by intermolecular forces. Solids have a definite shape and fill a container. Having said this, there are different atomic structures that solids have depending on the composition of the solid.</string>
    <string name="sigma_bonds_content">A sigma bond is formed between two orbitals that overlap in end to end fashion,as seen by the image above. All bonds (single, double, triple) have one sigma bond. A sigma bond is stronger than a pi bond.</string>
    <string name="second_order_content">In a second order reaction, the reaction rate depends either on the concentrations of one-second order reactant or two first-order reactants. In other words, the sum of the exponent in the rate law must equal 2. When graphed over time, 1/concentration of the reactant is a straight line with the slope of -k, while the 1/concentration of the product yields a straight line with a slope of k.</string>
    <string name="second_law_content">The second law of thermodynamics states that that the state of entropy of the entire universe will always increase over time. The second law also states that the changes in the entropy in the universe can never be negative. In a simpler sense, as time increases, a system will become more disordered.</string>
    <string name="references_content">The following sources were used in researching the content/images.   • chem.libretexts.org/   • chemcollective.org/   • acs.org/   • chemed.chem.purdue.edu/genchem  • ocw.mit.edu/high-school/chemistry   • khanacademy.org/science/chemistry</string>
    <string name="reaction_rates_content">The reaction rate is the speed at which reactants get converted into products. Four factors affect the reaction rate.   1. Concentration of reactant: Increasing the concentration of one or more reactants will often increase the rate of reaction  2. Surface area of reactant: The more surface area exposed by the reactant, the faster the rate of reaction  3. Temperature: An increase in temperature will generally increase the reaction rate.  4. Presence of a catalyst: A catalyst is a substance that accelerates a reaction without being consumed. Having a catalyst will increase the reaction rate.   The image above shows the derivation of the reaction rate from a generic chemical equation. Note that the reactants will have a negative sign, since the reactants are being consumed in the reaction.</string>
    <string name="rate_laws_content">A rate law is an equation that links the reaction rate with the concentrations or pressures of the reactants. The variable k is known as the rate constant and is specific to the given temperature/ Changing the temperature will change the rate constant. We will use rate laws to determine the reaction order of equations in future sections.</string>
    <string name="quantum_numbers_content">Quantum numbers are rules we must follow when we describe orbitals. The n describes the energy level, so this cannot be 0 or negative. The l value corresponds to the subshell of an atom(0 = s, 1 = p, 2 = d...), so this must be less than the n value. The m(l) value refers to the angular momentum, while the m(s) value refers to the spin. Since the spin can only be either positive or negative, this can only take on to values, +1/2 or -1/2.</string>
    <string name="pressure_solubility_content">Pressure effects on solubility are only significant for gasses dissolved in liquids. This can be described by Henry\'s law, shown in the image above. By using Le Chatlier\'s principle, a decrease in partial pressure means the concentration of gas in the liquid decreases as well, causing solubility to decrease. The opposite is true; a partial pressure increase means the concentration of gas in the liquid increases as well, meaning the solubility also increases.</string>
    <string name="polar_covalent_bonding_content">As previously mentioned, covalent bonding involves the sharing of electrons. However, sometimes, the electrons may be shared unevenly. This is due to one of the atoms being bonded having a much higher electronegativity than the other. When this happens, the more electronegative atom will pull electrons towards it. This phenomenon happens in water, where oxygen is more electronegative than hydrogen, and thus, electrons tend to be closer to the oxygen atom.</string>
    <string name="pi_bonds_content">A pi bond is formed between the overlap of the lobes (sides) of the orbitals. A single bond will have no pi bonds, while a double bond will have one, and a triple bond will have two.</string>
    <string name="ph_scale_content">The pH scale is used to measure how acidic ot basic a substance is. An acidic substance will have a pH of lower than 7, a basic substance will have a pHof greater than 7, and pure water will have a pH of 7. The pH scale is logaramithic and is based on the concentration of protons(H+), as pH = -log[H+].   Sometime, pOH is used as a measure of hydroxide ions, where pOH = -log[OH-]. An important relationship to note is pOH = 14- pH. The 14 comes from the self-ionisation constant of water. In simpler terms, pOH is reverse of pH; a lower pOH is basic, while a higher pOH is acidic.</string>
    <string name="photon_content">The photon is the fundamental unit of electromagentic radiation. In other words, a photon is the basic unit of light. Photons travel at 3.0 * 10^8 m/s. This constant is known as c, the speed of light. An important fact is that photons do not contain charge or mass, explaining why these properties are identical in light as well.</string>
    <string name="phase_diagram_content">Phase diagrams depict what phase a substance will be in at a particular temperature and pressure. A general phase diagram looks like the image above, with a low temperature/high pressure corresponding to a solid phase and a high temperature/low pressure corresponding to a gas phase. There are a few important parts of the graph that should be noted.   The triple point is the point at which the substance is at equilibrium across all three phases. In other words, the substance is equally a solid, liquid, and a gas at this point.   The critical point is the point at which the liquid and gas phases of the substance coexist and have the same density. This is typically the end of the equilibrium curve, as the substance can not be more liquified if pressure increases.</string>
    <string name="phase_changes_table">Below is a summary of phase changes and their appropriate names. The specifics of the phase changes will be discussed in the Thermodynamics section.</string>
    <string name="periodic_table_blocks">These are the blocks of the periodic table. These blocks are relevant for viewing how electrons fill up orbitals in atoms, as well as for seeing the different shapes of orbitals.</string>
    <string name="parts_of_wave_content">Crest: high point of a wave  \n\nTrough: low point of a wave   \n\nAmplitude: distance from center line to crest/trough.   \n\nWavelength: distance between two crests/troughs   \n\nCycle: consists of one crest and one trough   \n\nFrequency: number of cycles that pass through per unit time. This is inversely proportional to wavelength(i.e. a higher frequency = lower wavelength). A higher frequency means a higher energy.</string>
    <string name="noble_gases_content">"Noble Gases are found in the right-most column of the periodic table in group 18. Noble gases do not have any charge.

Some characteristics of noble gasses include:
  - because their outer valence shell is full, noble gases are not reactive
  - exist as gasses as room temperature
  - very low boiling and melting points"</string>
    <string name="neutralization_content">A neutralization reaction occurs when an acid and base combine to form water and a salt. The water comes from the combination of the H+ in the acid and OH- in the base. A neutralization of a strong acid and strong base will have a pH of 7, while a neutralization of a strong acid and weak base will have a pH of less than 7 and a neutralization of a strong base and weak acid will have a pH of greater than 7.</string>
    <string name="network_solids">Network solids consist of atoms covalently bonded throughout the crystal structure. Network solids typically are hard and have high melting points (not as high as ionic solids, however). Common examples of network solids include silicon dioxide and diamonds.</string>
    <string name="molecular_solids_content">Molecular solids consist of atoms held together by Van der Waal\'s forces or IMFs (i.e. there are no covalent or ionic bonds between the atoms). Due to this, molecular solids tend to be softer and have lower boiling points. The image above is a model of solid carbon dioxide, an example of a molecular solid.</string>
    <string name="metals_vs_nonmetals_content">"As seen by the image above, the periodic table is composed primarily of metals. Metals lie on the left and the center, while nonmetals lie on the ride.

Compared to nonmetals, metals tend to be/have:
  - good conductors of heat and electricity
  - harder and shinier
  - malleable and ductile.

Metalloids share properties of both metals and nonmetals."</string>
    <string name="metallic_solids_content">Metallic solids consist of metal atoms and electrons which are delocalized throughout the entire solid. Examples of such solids include solid copper, silver, and gold. Metallic solids are held together by metallic bonds, the force of attraction between the positive metal atoms and the negativly charged electrons. Because electrons can flow freely, metallic solids are good conductors of heat and electricity. They also are lusterous(reflect light), have high boiling points, and are malleable.</string>
    <string name="le_chatliers_principle">
        "To understand solubility, we must first understand Le Chatlier\'s Principle. This principle describes the effects of a change in pressure, temperature, or concentration of a reactant in a reaction. We shall see how the reaction changes when each variable is changed.

1. Change in concentration: For a change in concentration, the reaction will shift in such a manner such that the substance being changed will be replaced if removed, or consumed if added. If a reactant has an increase in concentration, the reaction will shift towards products, and if there is a decrease in concentration, the reaction will shift towards reactants. On the contrary, if a product has an increase in concentration, the reaction will shift towards reactants, and if decreased, the reaction will shift towards products.

2. Change in pressure: For a change in pressure, the reaction will move in the direction needed to counteract the change. If pressure is increased, the reaction will shift to the side with fewer molecules. Meanwhile, a decrease in pressure will cause the reaction to shift to the side with greater molecules, so as to produce more molecules and increase pressure. Note that if the number of molecules on both sides are the same, changing pressure does not shift the reaction.

3. Change in temperature: For a change in temperature, we must know if the reaction is endothermic (heat is a reactant) or exothermic (heat is a product). For a temperature increase, the reaction will shift towards the products if endothermic, or towards reactants if exothermic. Similarly, for a temperature decrease, the reaction will shift towards the products if exothermic, or towards reactants if endothermic."</string>
    <string name="ldfs_content">London Dispersion Forces (LDFs) are the most basic type of IMF. All molecules will have IMFs with other molecules. LDFs result from temporary dipole moments created by an uneven distribution of electrons. Typically, two nonpolar molecules will only have the LDF IMF. An important trend is the larger the molecules (in terms of molar mass), the stronger the LDF.</string>
    <string name="kmt_content">The Kinetic Molecular Theory (KMT) describes how particles interact when in proximity. Particles are in constant motion and will collide with each other or the container walls. However, this does not cause the energy of the system to change. The temperature of a gas is dependent on the average kinetic energy of the gas particles. A higher average kinetic energy correlates to a higher temperature, and vice versa.</string>
    <string name="ionization_energy_content">Ionization energy is the ammount of energy needed to remove a valence electron from an atom. As you move up a group, and from left to right across a period, ionization energy increases. This means that it becomes harder to remove a valence electron.   As you go left to right across a period, the force of attraction becomes stronger between the nucleus and valence electrons, due to the higher positive charge in the nucleus. As a result, it becomes more difficult to remove a valence electron.   Meanwhile, as you go down a group, more orbitals are added, which causes the distance of the valence electrons and nucleus to increase. This increased distance decreases the pull the nucleus as on the valence electrons, and thus, it is easier to remove a valence electron.</string>
    <string name="ionic_solids_content">Ionic solids are composed of cations(positive atoms) and anions (negative atoms). Due to the opposite charges, the atoms within an ionic solid are attracted to each other. When dissolved in water, the ionic solid will breakup into these ions, which will causes electrons to flow freely allowing electric current to be generated. Ionic solids also tend to have higher boiling points due to stronger attractions between atoms.</string>
    <string name="ionic_bonding">Ionic bonding typically takes place between a metal and nonmetal. It involves the transferring of electrons. In the picture above the Na atom will give an electron to the F atom. Both atoms require 8 electrons in their outer shell to be stable. Since fluorine has 7 valence electrons, it simply needs the one electron that sodium has in its outer shell. This will lead to both atoms having full outer shells.</string>
    <string name="ion_dipole_forces">Ion Dipole Forces occur between a ion and a polar molecule. These are even stronger than H-bonding. This is due to the significant opposite charges between the end of the polar molecule and the ion. However, ion dipole forces are still nowhere as strong as bonds.</string>
    <string name="intro_to_titrations_content">Titration is the slow addition of one solution of a known concentration(a titrant) to a known volume of another solution of unknown concentration until the reaction reaches neutralization, which is often indicated by a color change. Titrations are a common labaratory practice and are helpful in determining the concentration of an unknown solution.</string>
    <string name="intro_to_kinetics_content">In chemistry, we often want to see how fast reactions proceed based upon their reactants and their products. Reactions will proceed to a state called equilibrium, where there the concentrations of reactants and products no longer change. The study of how fast a reaction proceeds to equilibrium is called kinetics.</string>
    <string name="intro_periodic_table_content">The Periodic Table is the fundamental resource used in Chemistry. It lays out all of the elements, with their atomic mass and atomic number. Furthermore, properties of elements can be predicted based on where they lie on the Periodic Table.</string>
    <string name="intro_heating_curves_content">Heating curves show what state of matter a substance will be in at a particular temperature. As more heat is added, the temperature will rise. When the substance is undergoing a phase change, the substance will not increase in temperature, because the heat is going towards the phase change. This section is denoted by flat lines in the graph, while the increase in temperature is denoted by the sloped lines.</string>
    <string name="ideal_gas_law_content">The previous laws can be explained by the equation above. One can rearrange the equation in order to solve for the needed information. Notice that from the equation, one can see that pressure and volume have an inversly proportional relationship, while pressure and temperature and pressure and # of moles have a directly proportional relationship. The universal gas constant R, is a constant number that relates all of the previous terms. It can change based on the units. For example, it also takes on the value, 8.314 J/mol.</string>
    <string name="hybrid_orbitals_content">Hybridization occurs when orbitals of different atoms overlap. This can cause changes in molecular geometry and bonding. For example, sigma and pi bonds are formed through hybridization. We name hybrdization by the orbitals that are overlapping (s,p,d, or rarely, f).</string>
    <string name="h_bonding_content">Hydrogen bonding (H-bonding) is a special type of IMF that involves a an electrostatic attraction between an H atom and the highly electronegative N, O, or F atoms and lone electron pairs. H-bonding is the strongest of the IMFs. H-bonding in water allows it to have special properties, such as a high boiling point.</string>
    <string name="halogens_content">"Halogens are found in the second right-most column of the periodic table in group 17. Halogens form ions with a charge of -1.

Some characteristics of halogens include:
   - lower boiling and melting points than metals
   - highly reactive
   - colors grow darker down the group"</string>
    <string name="groups_and_periods_content">Groups are vertical columns of the Periodic Table, while periods are horizontal rows. There are 7 periods and 18 groups on the Periodic Table \n\nPeriods are relevant for finding the energy level of the outmost orbital of an atom. Meanwhile, elements in some groups have defining characteristics which help classify them as a member of that group  \n\nSome major groups include:\n  - Alkali metals (Group 1)\n  - Alkaline Earth metals (Group 2)\n  - Transition metals (Groups 3 - 12)\n  - Halogens (Group 17)\n  - Noble Gases(Group 18)</string>
    <string name="grahams_law_content">Graham\'s law is the equation used in order to compare rates of effusion for two different gasses. Note that gases with smaller molar masses will effuse faster.</string>
    <string name="g_neg_content">As we have seen previously, the equation for Gibb\'s free energy is dependent on both the change in enthalpy and the change in entropy. The chart above shows when delta G is negative based on the magnitudes of delta H and delta S.</string>
    <string name="gibbs_free_energy_content">Gibb\'s free energy helps us to predict whether a reaction will be spontaneous or not. The equation for this is in the picture above. There are three important scenarios:    1. If delta G is negative, the reaction is spontaneous in the forwards direction 2. If delta G is positive, the reaction is spontaneous in the reverse direction 3. If delta G is 0, the reaction is in equilibrium</string>
    <string name="gas_properties_content">Gases are a state of matter which have do not have a definite shape nor can fill up a container. In a gas, particles are spread the furthest apart and move the quickest. Gasses can be a mixture, indivisual atoms (neon gas), or elemental molecules (oxygen gas). Gases tend to be invisible.  Gases are affected by temperature, pressure, number of moles, and volume. There are distinct laws that explain the relationships between these characteristics in gases.</string>
    <string name="first_order_content">In a first order reaction, the reaction rate depends linearly on one of the reactant concentrations. When graphed over time, the natural logarithm of concentration of the reactant is a straight line with the slope of -k, while the concentration of the product would have a slope of ln k.</string>
    <string name="first_law_content">The first law of thermodynamics is the application of the conservation of energy principle thermodynamic processes. In other words, energy through the means of heat, work, and/or internal energy cannot be created nor destroyed. The equation above helps illustrate this law.</string>
    <string name="entropy_content">Entropy is a function that describes the disorder of molecules based on the number of different arrangements available to them in a given system/reaction.  A good analogy is thinking about a kitchen. There might be a state where the kitchen is clean and everything is in place. However, as time goes on, the kitchen becomes more and more messy. In other words, the kitchen turns to a state of messiness. How messy the kitchen gets depends on the number of items in said kitchen. The ideas is similar in a system, where the disorder depends on the number of arrangements of molecules.</string>
    <string name="enthalpy_content">Enthalpy is the internal energy of the system plus the product of pressure and volume. At constant pressure, the heat evolved (either released or absorbed) in a system is equal to the change in enthalpy in that system.</string>
    <string name="energy_levels_content">Electrons in atoms have distinct energy levels. The further from the nucleus the orbit is, the higher the energy level. These energy levels are quantized, meaning that electrons can only have the energies that correspond to an orbital of the atom.   If an electron wants to move to a higher energy orbital, it must only gain the energy needed to move to the energy level. For example, if the first orbital has an energy of 5 eV and the second orbital has an energy of 12 eV, the electron must gain 7 eV, no more or more less. Likewise, if the electron wants to move to a lower energy level, it must lose energy. Using the previous example, the electron would need to lose 7 eV to from the second to the first energy level.</string>
    <string name="energy_content">The energy of a system is the sum of the potential and kinetic energies of the particles in the system. The faster particles move, the more kinetic energy the particles have. Also, the further apart particles are, the more potential energy they have.</string>
    <string name="electron_configuration_content">In order to denote what orbitals and electrons an atom has, we must use a certain notation, called electron configuration. Electron configuration has many rules that need to be followed in order to get an accurate notation. These rules deal with starting from the lowest energy levels and building up, the number of electrons per suborbital (2), and that every orbital in a subshell is singly occupied with one electron before any more electrons are added.</string>
    <string name="electron_affinity_content">Electron affinity is the change in energy (in kilojoules) when an electron is added to a neutral atom. The energy change is negative when an electron is added to a non-metal, because the atom gives off energy to form an anion. Therefore, a more negative number indicates a higher electron affinity.   As you go across a period, the number of outer (valence) electrons increases. This means that atoms will be more likely to gain electrons so that they have a stable outer shell.   As you go down a group, more orbitals get added. Thus, the distance between the valence electrons and the nucleus increases. Because of this, not as much energy is released when an electron is added.</string>
    <string name="disclaimer_content">While the information within this app has been checked, ChemEasy does not have any responsibility towards your results/grades. Use this app at your own discretion. Also note that the scope of this app is for AP Chemistry/introductory general chemistry classes. The information you seek may not be found in this app.</string>
    <string name="diff_content">When introduced to a new container, gasses tend to move from a higher concentration to a lower concentration, or in other words, they tend to spread out. This process is called diffusion. All gases will undergo diffusion, because gas particles are in constant random motion. The rate of diffusion is dependent on temperature and size of the gas particles \n \n Effusion refers to a gas escaping its container through a miniscule hole. This is dependent on the molar mass of the gas. A gas in a container with porous whole will eventually completely escape.</string>
    <string name="ddfs_content">Dipole Dipole Forces(DDFs) occur between a polar and nonpolar molecule, or two polar molecules. Note that any IMFs involving polar molecules will have both LDFs and DDFs. Dipole dipole interactions are stronger than LDFs due to attractions involving opposite charges on the atoms.</string>
    <string name="covalent_bonding_content">Covalent bonding involves the sharing of electrons. It is found in bonds between nonmetals. Atoms share electrons so that both atoms can be stable, as seen in the above example. In carbon dioxide, the carbon needs to share 4 atoms, while each oxygen needs to share 2 atoms, so that all atoms can have 8 valence electrons.</string>
    <string name="cooling_curves_bonding">Cooling curves are similar to heating curves, except that energy is leaving the system, lowering the temperature. The substance will start out as a gas and then cool to a liquid and then to a solid. Refer to the graph above for more details.</string>
    <string name="common_ion_effect">The common ion effect states that there will be a decrease in solubility of an ionic compound if it is added to preexisting mixture which already has one of the ions in the added compound. This can be explained through Le Chatlier\'s Principle, in that one is essentially increasing the ions in the reaction, so the reaction will shift towards the reactants in order to consume some of the excess ions.</string>
    <string name="chemical_bonding_content">In order for an atom to be stable, it needs to have a full outer valence shell. However, other than noble gasses, most atoms will not have a full outer shell. Therefore, in order for the atom to become stable, it bonds with other atoms, either through losing/gaining electrons or sharing electrons. The ways atoms can obtain a full outer shell will be discussed further.</string>
    <string name="charles_law_content">Charles Law explores the relationship between the temperature and volume of a gas. As the temperature increases, the volume of the container will increase. This makes sense because an increase in temperature will cause the gas particles to spread out, thus causing the gas to occupy a greater ammount of space, increasing volume.</string>
    <string name="bronsted_lowry_definition_content">The Brønsted Lowry theory states that acids are proton (H+) donors while bases are proton (H+) acceptors. If a compound acts as both a proton acceptor and proton donor, it is known as amphoteric. This builds on the Arrhenius theory, but a substance no longer needs to be composed of protons (H+) or hydroxide (OH-) to be classified as an acid or base.   This theory leads to another important idea: conjugate acids and conjugate bases. A conjugate acid is the result of a proton added to a base. On the other hand, a conjugate base is the result of a proton removed from an acid. Refer to the image above for more information.</string>
    <string name="boyles_law_content">Boyle\'s Law explores the relationship between the pressure and volume of a gas. As the pressure of a a gas increases, the volume of the container will decrease. An increase in pressure will cause the gas particles to come closer together, which means the gas takes up a lower ammount of space, causing the volume to decrease. Likewise, an decrease in pressure would cause volume to increase, as now the particles are farther apart.</string>
    <string name="avogadros_law_content">Avogadro\'s Law explores the relationship between number of moles and volume of a gas. As the number of moles increases, the volume of a gas will increase. This is due to the fact that as more particles are added, there will be more space available for the gas to spread, which increases the volume.</string>
    <string name="atomic_radius_content">Atomic radius is the distance from an atoms nucleus to its outermost election. This figure increases from right to left and from top to bottom.   In terms of groups, moving downwards adds additional orbitals to the atom, making the atomic radius larger.   In terms of periods, as you move to the right, more electrons and protons get added. The stronger positive charge from the nucleus pulls the outer electrons closer, which causes the atomic radius to decrease.</string>
    <string name="arrhenius_definition_content">The Arrhenius theory of acids and bases states that an Arrhenius acid is a substance that dissociates in water and increases the concentration of hydrogen ions (H+). The H+ ions will combine with water to form hydronium ions (H3O+). Meanwhile, an Arrhenius base increases the concentration of hydroxide (OH-) ions. An example of an Arrhenius acid and Arrhenius base is in the image above."</string>
    <string name="alkaline_earth_metals_content">"The Alkaline Earth Metals are found in Group 2, or the second leftmost column of the Periodic Table (as seen by the image above).

Alkaline Earth metals form ions that carry a +2 charge and typically have the following characteristics:
  - shiny and silvery
  - not readily found in nature
  - have higher melting and boiling points than alkali earth metals
  - are malleable(can be hammered) and ductile(can be made into wires)"</string>
    <string name="alkali_metals_content">"The Alkali Metals are found in Group 1, or the left most column of the Periodic Table (as seen by the image above).

Alkali metals form ions that carry a +1 charge and have the following characteristics:
  - have low boiling and melting points
  - relatively soft and can be cut with a knife
  - reactive in water
  - have low densities."</string>
    <string name="about_the_app_content">This app was made by Atharva Doshi, a student at The Ohio State University. While taking general chemistry, I thought of making an app that would act as a chemistry reference guide. After an year of work, this app has finally come to fruition.  Within this app you will find important sections of chemistry in a slide based format. Simply swipe to access the slides. Note that some sections will allow you to take a quiz to test your understanding of the material.</string>
</resources>
